<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ASCII'?>
<comments>
  <note value="0"/>
  <note value="1"/>
  <note value="2">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Finland">One has to give credit for Catan for being a groundbraking game that paved the way for what modern boardgames are today. There is something appealing in the the theme, but games have evolved tremendously in the last decade and while groundbraking in the 90's, Catan simply falls short these days.  Simply put, I find Catan to be an awful game of dice-rolling randomness that takes way too long to boot. It looks nicer than Monopoly, but gameplay-wise the latter is better.. and that's saying a lot, since it's not much of a game either. As a family game Catan might be passable, but it creates so much frustration that I doubt it would be much fun.   Even the iPhone app is waste of money.. I would not play it unless I wanted to piss myself off on purpose. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Australia">boring!</comment>
  </note>
  <note value="3">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I don't have any visceral hate for the game, I just wish it didn't take as long to play. One thing in particular that I dislike is similar to Terra Mystica; the critical decisions are all front loaded in the game (settlement placements and early expansion), and there is a permanence in the area/point controls. Catan just takes less time is the upside.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Perhaps I just over-played this one in its prime. Mostly, I just don't like games that take an hour and a half to play but you can often tell who's going to win in the first 30 minutes (or at least who is going to lose... but they're still stuck playing). </comment>
  </note>
  <note value="4">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">While I appreciate its significance as a gateway game, I do not like how bad you can get screwed thanks to dicerolls.  I also do not like the relative value of some of the starting town positions versus others.  I hope that Anno 1701 gets printed in the US, to supplant Settlers as the gateway Catan game.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I used to think this game was the greatest thing ever.  But now I'm not too sure.  Too random and luck based.  I prefer my board games "German".  As in no luck involved.   Still a good game to introduce non gamers to a world of games out there that are a whole hell of a lot better than Monopoly!  For that it absolutly rocks!</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="South Korea">Reviewed on my blog.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Far too random for my liking, and a bit simplistic.  For a real resource trading game, try Avalon Hill's "Civilization."</comment>
  </note>
  <note value="5">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Takes WAY too long for what it is.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Australia">Unrecorded plays ~ 10</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="">Bueno y sencillo</comment>
  </note>
  <note value="6">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">EXPANSION: 5-6 Player EXTRA:  Catan: Board (2-6 size) ,  Card Holder</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Germany">I was too young and/or too ignorant to get into this game when it first became all the rage in the mid-nineties. And when I finally got to play it, I just didn't care all that much about it - maybe it's because of the other, more refined games I'd learned to enjoy by then.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Haven't played this one in years, and haven't played it since getting back into gaming.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">I feel it is far too complicated to be suggested as a gateway game. Ticket to ride and Carcassonne both are easier to introduce.  Major strategy elements are decided in the first few minutes of play, making it incredibly unforgiving to newcomers.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">We were late to the game in playing Settlers and had already worked through Dominion and Carcassonne dozens of times before this one hit the table. We've played it once or twice, but with so many other great, and newer, games in our collection, there is no reason to ever play it. Still, it is one of the new classics.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Australia">Although a definite classic, I find too much luck in Settlers to be able to fully enjoy a playthrough. I will play it, but rarely suggest it.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Canada">The game's a masterpiece, even though I hate the dice rolling.  The game that turned me on to German/designer games, as well as all of my friends.  Don't play it much anymore, but it's definitely earned a permanent place in my all time top 10.  Own the [boardgame=926]Cities &amp; Knights[/boardgame], [boardgame=27760]Traders &amp; Barbarians[/boardgame], [boardgame=135378]Explorers &amp; Pirates[/boardgame], and [boardgame=86669]Helpers[/boardgame] expansions.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Belgium">We never play the base version any more, but it's a nice intro to the hobby, I guess</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">The game that started this obsession for many people.  This was the first Eurogame I played, and I got introduced to it in college and played a bunch with several friends.  Unfortunately, I don't have much use for this game anymore because I don't enjoy playing it, my game group has long outgrown it, and I don't even use it as a gateway anymore because I have better games for that.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Thailand">&#3648;&#3585;&#3617;&#3649;&#3619;&#3585;&#3607;&#3637;&#3656;&#3607;&#3635;&#3651;&#3627;&#3657;&#3648;&#3586;&#3657;&#3634;&#3623;&#3591;&#3585;&#3634;&#3619; &#3627;&#3621;&#3633;&#3591;&#3654;&#3629;&#3629;&#3585;&#3649;&#3609;&#3623;&#3648;&#3593;&#3618;&#3654;&#3607;&#3637;&#3656;&#3592;&#3632;&#3648;&#3621;&#3656;&#3609; &#3649;&#3605;&#3656;&#3606;&#3657;&#3634;&#3651;&#3627;&#3657;&#3604;&#3637;&#3605;&#3657;&#3629;&#3591;&#3651;&#3594;&#3657; event &#3585;&#3634;&#3619;&#3660;&#3604;&#3648;&#3607;&#3656;&#3634;&#3609;&#3633;&#3657;&#3609; &#3652;&#3617;&#3656;&#3588;&#3656;&#3629;&#3618;&#3594;&#3629;&#3610;&#3607;&#3629;&#3618;&#3648;&#3605;&#3659;&#3634;&#3648;&#3607;&#3656;&#3634;&#3652;&#3619;&#3621;&#3656;&#3632;&#3651;&#3594;&#3657;&#3649;&#3621;&#3657;&#3623;&#3627;&#3604;&#3627;&#3641;&#3656;</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">130929 The thrill of waiting to see the dice go your way gets a little old.  But no denying its thrilling, as well as hoping your opponent doesn't do something.  Maybe I like the tenseness of these games, but I don't like the source of the tenseness (the secretly hoping your opponent doesn't make a blocking play).  100808 Dice.  Otherwise fun and thrilling, but the dice part kinda drives me nuts...</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Look, Catan got me into gaming. I can't deny that I've loved and played it a lot. But Catan (especially with no expansions) just isn't interesting anymore. I have played it upwards of thirty times online against AIs, and as such I'm pretty much played out on the game. Diversify your hexes, go for largest army or longest road (whichever has less competition), and trade only as much as necessary. Spread out and diversify your resources early, then bulk up on cities mid-game. I don't know, strategies vary, but I just feel like I'm always playing Catan on rails. It feels solved.   So yes, Catan is a great gateway game. It's exciting for new players who've never played a German-style game before. But I don't need to buy the game, or its expansions -- there's no need to. I've got plenty of other games that scratch that itch, and while I'm happy to recommend it, there's no need for me to personally own it. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Minority opinion:  I don&amp;#039;t like this as much as most people.  Glad it started the German game craze though.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Catan is the first high end board game I played. It is a good, fun game, although it is a little dry.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="South Africa">A classic. The one drawback I can think of is that the luck of dice (especially if 7 is thrown repeatedly) can swing things uncontrollably towards one player. Better might have been to let 7 be some other action, and make the robber a less common roll, like 2 or 12, say. The 3-player game works much better than the 4-player because in the 4-player one player always gets locked out with no choice but to twiddle their thumbs.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Canada">My mother has this game. On its own it is ok, a bit too simple for my taste, but it is one of my favorites with the "Cities and Knights" expansion.   I like it fine with 2 players.</comment>
  </note>
  <note value="7">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Canada">It has a good, quick pace, and works well with three players. Too much luck, not enough strategy though. The best part of the game is picking your initial settlements.  ---- (bought)</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">Bizarrely, my copy of this game, which I have had for over a year, is unplayed.  Instead I've played on other people's sets at a local gaming club.  Despite being quite a good player I have failed to ever win at this, and it is a source of personal frustration. Okay, its got a large random factor with the dice and a popularity/shouting factor with the trading and the cards throw an extra random element into the mix, but I should win sometime, surely....?</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Rachel's half</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Played heavily before I began tracking plays</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">An extremely simple and enjoyable game; but not quite as deep as those I usually enjoy.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I don't understand why everyone seems to like this game so much. It's made of good quality materials but the gameplay for me is just...bleh.  I play it quite a bit however because it's one of the few games I can get my whole family to play.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="">The game mechanics are mildly interesting at best but the metagame makes it great: encourage table talk, make side deals, play opponents off each other and weasel your way to victory.  </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Netherlands">A little bit too simple without add-ons.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">Good fun. Can suffer a bit from 'I dont like you ****. So no I wont give you this resource card'. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">+ Simple gameplay + Nice components - I see no incentive to trade - Can have too much downtime</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Complete with components in excellent condition, box very slightly dished on top and one corner on box bottom shows small crease and minor ding  BIN 20</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Simple euro with good interaction and planning aspects.  I enjoy playing this with my kids (ages 8 and 6).</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Australia">A modern classic.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Very good game.  If you fall behind early, it can be very boring though.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Like many, this started it all for me. It has lost the appeal it once had though. It could be the setup, but if that were it, Twilight Imperium (3rd Ed.) would really never get played ever again. :)  That can't be it. It's a keeper, as it's MY gateway game.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Spain">Juego encantador y muy adictivo, recomendable para no jugadores y f&#233;minas. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">German language edition, wooden pieces</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I really enjoy this game.  Most of my play time has been logged on the 360, but I don't record that here.  I'm not allowed to play with my girlfriend, cause I'm too cutthroat:(.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Australia">Classic, its an awesome gateway game.  Lots of player interaction.  A rather high luck factor though.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">This game is da bomb! In the early 00's I decided to start looking for games like I used to play back in the 80's and 'Settlers' introduced me to Eurogames and the Das Buch variants make this a game I'll want to play forever. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="">Good game, but I think that there are better games now.  The theme and artwork are also lacking compared to some more modern games.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">A great interactive and social experience. Easy to teach and hilarious when you both swap the same cards (i.e. wood for wood) with a fellow player as you have asked for the resource in the wrong way for the umpteenth time. Great re-playability and the fishermen mini-extension balances the non-harbour costal settlements. A great family game and a classic. Would have loved to have played this in 1995 when it was released - the UK was just not as exposed to these "euro" games for some reason. If my mum will play and enjoy this game, trust me, ANYONE will.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Germany">50 EUR including Cities &amp; Knight + 5-6 players + event card expansions  Good game with a lot of interaction and communication between players, but just to simple. So I am curious how much the add-ons make it more complex like the cardgame.</comment>
  </note>
  <note value="8">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Colombia">I don't know why I haven't buy this game. I was the first non-monopolyriskclue board game I played and I still enjoy it.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="England">I would originally have rated this as a 9 but I'm bored with it now even with the numerous scenarios around. If the game lasts under an hour it's fine but you get the occassional one that just drags. However, I still think it's the perfect gateway game and will always select it when introducing newbies. I always preferred the Seafarers version but am quite happy with just the base game now. Cities &amp; Knights tries to make the game something that it's not. Das Buch has some interesting scenarios though.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Russia">&#1054;&#1090;&#1089;&#1091;&#1090;&#1089;&#1090;&#1074;&#1091;&#1077;&#1090; &#1086;&#1076;&#1085;&#1072; &#1082;&#1072;&#1088;&#1090;&#1086;&#1095;&#1082;&#1072; &#1052;&#1054;&#1053;&#1054;&#1055;&#1054;&#1051;&#1048;&#1071;.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I like the game but the only problem I have with it is there is a lot of luck involved with the die role. Don't get me wrong, I like some luck in my games. But this one requires too much luck in order to win. For example, I played my 13 year old daughter and son and we all kept rolling 9s all of the time, which gave my daughter tons of resources. She clobbered us, getting 10 points before my son and I got to five points. I bought this game expecting a lot more strategy and was dissapointed.  Edit: I have played this a few more times and, while I still don't see a ton of strategy in this game, I am seeing more possibilities. I think the expansions will probably go a long way toward increasing replayability. I increased the rating from a 7 to a 8.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">One of my favorite 4 player games.  A fine mix of luck and strategy.  You feel like you have quite a few options each turn and trading is awesome.  Great replay value.  Once you get comfortable with the game, I would recommend the cities and knights expansion. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">My gateway game. It will always hold a special spot for me for that! </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Great game but not for me.  I don't want to beg the other player for a log or some wool.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Australia">iOS version</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Plays and dates estimated.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Portugal">Excellent game to introduce new players to board games, especially because they might win (it happened in my last two games), but also because the rules are simple and fast to learn. Although I like it, it's too luck driven. If the dice don't like you, you won't stand a chance.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Canada">Classic. It all started with this one. Need I say more?</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">A classic in it's own time, and what can you say about Settlers that has not already been said? If you don't own it and you think you're gamer then you're sadly mistaken...</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">This is the gateway game. I'm almost always willing to play.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United Kingdom">A game best served with inebriants for maximum 'Got wood?' value. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Poland">IMO very easy and good game </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Hong Kong">My first impression is: this is the best family game in 20 years and that's before I even knew about BGG! After my eyes have been opened wide by BGG, I would still say this' the best family game in 20 years (over the likes of Monopoly, Scrabble, Risk) but my attention was diverted to those of Puerto Rico, Twilight Imperium III, and Android... Thus I brought down my grading for Catan to 8 from 10 as I would like to try out the others first (and the BGG grading is based on willingness to play). But my impression remained the same for Catan: it's the best family game in 20 years!</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">A great game for welcoming non-gamers to games. Simple, elegant game with excellent replayability, especially when you're incorporating the modularity of the Seafarers expansions.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">My first "German style" game and I love it.  Would love to play more, but need at least three people.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">This was my gateway game!  Settlers was the first Euro style game I ever played...really the first nontraditional game ever for me, and ever since I've become obsessed!  Still enjoy Settlers.  I took to the mechanic instantly and still love to play.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Love it - will still play at any time.  I love when a newbie to the hobby will gush about this "great new game called Settlers of Catan..."  Oh, let me open your eyes!  The gateway game.  If they don't like it, give it up and find a new friend, lol.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I'll be honest this was my first board game that I loved.  I still will play it today for its ease of play and with the expansions for new players and non-gamers.  TTR and Waterdeep have mostly replaced it for the gateways, but it still sneaks out from time to time :)</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">I love this game, there are so many strategies and so many ways to win that the replay value is virtually limitless. Radmonization of the game board ensures you will pretty much never play the same game twice. It seems overwhelming to new players who have never played but usually within 2-3 turns they seem catch on and always end up really enjoying it. This has become a new staple during family holidays &amp; birthdays, everyone always asks to make sure I brought it.</comment>
  </note>
  <note value="9">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Germany">The door in the board game world! absolutly awesome...</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Latvia">I love this game! It is near perfect. It plays well with 3, but really seems like a game for 2 couples. When we have 4 to play, it's Settlers at my house!</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">This game simply sets the standard for modern games. Simple, amazingly fun, really interesting play mechanics. My only gripe is the cost, just getting the core set and the Cities/Knights expansion, as well as the 6-player upgrade for both, will run you about $120. Ouch!</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Sweden">34</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Canada">My introduction to modern boardgames. </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">A classic.  </comment>
  </note>
  <note value="10">
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">A gold standard for game balance, replayability, and pacing.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="">3,4 p</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Any game that has win-win negotiating as the mechanic is ok by me </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">Own 3 copies of 3rd edition, 2 copies of the 2nd edition (1 complete and 1 missing a few purple road segments), and 1 copy of the wooden 15th Anniversary edition. Also have 2 Settlers wooden game boards, 2 sets of 4th edition replacement cards and 2 longest turn (negative victory point) cards.</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="Slovenia">Nice game for family and friends, base building and trading and possible twists in ending score</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">If I'm going to play a Euro, it should be exciting, and Settlers is certainly that.  The dice rolls really make the game--they let the drama of not getting what you need, of being forced to make new plans, rise up.  My only complaint is that you can be out of the game before your first turn if your initial set up isn't well thought out.  That is a huge barrier for new players versus experienced players, but the game seems to have done alright for itself.  Certainly worthy of its status, and I don't understand why it isn't ranked higher.  </comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">This was my introduction to European games, and it still stands as one of the very best.  Short enough to get played often, but long enough to be satisfying.  Simple enough to teach casual gamers to play (and they like and understand it), but still a very engaging and fun game.  Has lots of decision making and player interaction, and requires a good mix of luck, strategy, and trading.  Loving civilization-type games, I really like the way this one plays.  Also, I made my own board, which makes it look awesome: www.boardgamegeek.com/image/152673</comment>
    <comment game="Catan" game_id="13" location="United States">* Upped my rating from an 8 to a 10 as I realized that I would likely never turn a game of Settlers down.  It's a well distilled ruleset that epitomizes the "euro" game.  Simple enough for folks to grasp and play in a single evening, yet still provides plenty of opportunity for thinking and anaysis.</comment>
  </note>
</comments>
